帮你丈夫建造神庙
round the desert to help build your husband's temple.
不  贱民  你确实臭气熏天
No, you do stink, peasant,
但那比这味道更臭
but it's much worse than that.
可能是我放在地上的羚羊屎
Oh, it could be the gazelle dung I've put on the floor.
你为何这么做
Oh! Why on earth would you do that?
-防止那些老鼠靠近我的食物  -老鼠
- Keeps the rats away from food. - Rats!
他们确实这么干
也可能是那些墙  它们都是用粪便做得
Or, it could be the walls, they're made of manure,
恰逢上个月尼罗河淹过小屋
and the Nile flooded the hut last month,
所以它们有点  怎么说  粘乎乎的吧
so they're still a bit, how shall I put it, sweaty.
-我只能说我爱死这里了  -太好了
- I can tell I'm going to just love it here. - Great.
同时  在宫殿这边  晚餐时间到了
Meanwhile, over at the palace, it's dinner time.
拿着  贱民  尝尝这些
Here, peasant, try one of these.
这是什么  法老
What is it, my Pharaoh?
蜜汁蚱蜢
Locust in honey.
古埃及人的佳肴
真好吃
That's delicious.
我今晚想早点睡了
I feel I'm going to grab an early night.
我得在太阳出来前起床  这是当然的
I have to be up before the sun comes up. Well, obviously I do.
毕竟我可是唤醒太阳的男人
I'm the one who gets the sun up.
他们坚信是法老让太阳升起来
我刚开了个玩笑
I done a joke.
这才像话
That's more like it.
你不会相信的
You won't believe this,
王宫床上舒适的枕头
the royal palace has got beds
竟是用石头做得
with comfy pillows made of stone.
而且上厕所时得坐在像椅子一样的东西上
And a sort of seat thing that you sit on to go to toilet.
他们的脑子都进屎了吗
What will they think of next?
再看看贱民家中的晚餐时间
And it's also dinner time in the peasant hut.
不好意思  王后  我们这蚊子略多
Sorry, Your Majesty, we do get a lot of mosquitoes,
因为这里靠近尼罗河下游段
that's the downside of living near the Nile.
但好处是有尼罗河的灌溉
The plus side is that the Nile floods,
所以这里土地很肥沃
so the soil here is very fertile.
当洪水泛滥时  我们农民就休耕几个月
And when it does flood, we farmers get a few months off
去沙漠那边  为法老搬运两吨重的巨石
to go to the desert and drag around two-ton boulders for the Pharaoh.
但至少那可以让你远离这些蚊子
Ow! Well, at least it gets you away from all these mosquitoes.
也离那些致命的蝎子更近了
And nearer the deadly scorpions!
你不想要洋葱吗
Do you not want your onion?
-不许看着我  -不好意思
- Don't look at me. - Sorry.
你一定不会相信我在哪睡
You're not going to believe where I had to sleep.
地上铺些稻草就是床  你没听错
On some straw on the floor. Yes, that's right.
和这些羚羊屎一起睡在地上
On the floor with all the gazelle poop.
我身上绝对长虱子了
I swear I've got nits.
看看  这里就有一只
Oh, look, look, there's one.
奈菲尔塔利王后戴假发
我得扔了这假发
I'll have to throw this wig away.
《历史版交换女主人》  古埃及
交换女主人时间结束
The wife swap is at an end.
是时候让王室夫妻
And it's time for the royal couple
和贱民夫妻谈谈他们的体验
and the peasant couple to discuss their experiences.
我知道你在帮我建拉美西斯二世神庙
I understand you've been helping build my temple, the Ramessium.
这是你的无上光荣
What an honour for you.
我的19米高雕像怎样
How looks the 19-metre statue of me?
实在是太宏伟了  法老
Oh, it is magnificent, Pharaoh.
尽管没有本人这么赞
Although not as impressive as the real thing.
你的工作完成了  但我有好消息告诉你
Ah, your work is done! But I have some good news for you.
我要你在我的神庙旁边为我心爱的妻子
I would like you to build another massive temple alongside
再建一座巨大的神庙
for my favourite wife.
小拉美儿  你真是太贴心了【根据神庙名字译得
Oh, Romy baby, that's so sweet.
你也想要  是吗
Oh, you want one too, do you?
别占用任何假日【求校】
Don't book any holidays.
我们有谈过这个  Romy
We did actually discuss this, Romy.
是吗  我不记得了
Did we? I don't remember.
那么我们可以边喝棕榈酒边谈
Well, you had a lot of palm wine to drink.
但你从没吐露心声
Well, you don't speak up.
你觉得我们能起身了吗  亲爱的
Do you think we can get up now, love?
-我可不敢  -好吧
- I wouldn't risk it. - No.
奈菲尔塔利王后深受脱发折磨
Queen Nefertari suffered from alopecia,
所以她戴了假发
so she wore a wig.
昂贵的埃及假发是由十二万根头发制成
Expensive Egyptian wigs were made of 120,000 human hairs
并用蜂蜡固定
held in place by beeswax.
那是你的假发吗  王后
Is that a wig, Your Majesty?
管好你自己的蜂蜡就行【我不太理解他说这话是出自问方还是答方】
"Oh! Mind your own beeswax."
邪恶的维多利亚时代
亚历山大・格拉汉姆・贝尔是维多利亚时代
One of the most famous victorian inventors
最著名的发明家之一
was Alexander Graham Bell,
他发明了电话  很熟悉吧
who came up with the telephone - ring a bell?
但他的设计是由美国发明家
But his design was to be
托马斯・爱迪生进行改良的
improved by American inventor Thomas Edison.
祝各位今天好运
Good day to you.
爱迪生先生  你的电话【求校】
Mr Edison, telephone for you.
谢谢  神马意思
Thank you. What does it even mean?
不  我给你买了台电话  这是
No, I bought you a telephone, it's a new invention
亚历山大・格拉汉姆・贝尔新发明的
by this guy, Alexander Graham Bell.
我觉得你可能感兴趣
I thought it might interest you.
它和我们正在做得
It ties in nicely with the experiments we're doing
-声音传播实验相关  -真的吗
- on the transmission of sound. - Really?
有了它  你就可以通过电缆和别人说话
It allows you to talk to somebody down a cable.
可以和身处不同房间的人说话
You can talk to somebody in a different room
或许将来还能在不同大楼之间通话
and, maybe, who knows, one day in a different building.
太棒了  我们能试一试吗
Extraordinary! Well, can we try it?
当然  但贝尔先生要求我们
Of course! But Mr Bell insists
都得用官方通话问候语
that we use the official telephone greeting.
-是什么  -喂喂
- Which is? - Ahoy-hoy.
Bell希望所有人都说喂喂
作为打电话方  我得先说"喂喂"
As the caller, I have to say, "Ahoy-hoy" to you,
你回"喂喂"  这样就能知道
you say, "Ahoy-hoy" back, that way we know
-我们能听到对方说话  -明白
- we're receiving each other. - Understood.
准备好了吗  先生
Are you ready, sir?
-当然  -那就开始吧
- Oh, yes, indeed. - Here we go.
-喂喂  -你好
- Ahoy-hoy. - Hello.
错了  先生  你得回我"喂喂"
No, sir, you have to say, "Ahoy-hoy" back to me.
没错  我只是被它震惊到了
Yes, I was just shocked that it actually worked,
所以才会蹦出这种维多利亚式表达
so the Victorian expression of surprise crept out.
"你好"就相当于"天呐"
"Hello", as in, "Wow"!
你好曾用来表达惊叹之情
-我们再来一次吧  -好的
- Shall we try it again? - Yeah!
-喂喂  -你好
- Ahoy-hoy. - Hello.
-你又说你好了  -你也说了
- Hello, you said it again. - So did you.
我只是对你又这样表示惊奇
Well, I was surprised that you said it again.
但我还是被它震惊到了
Well, I'm still surprised it works.
好吧  先生  我们再试多一次
Hm. OK, sir, shall we try it one more time?
-喂喂  -你好
- Ahoy-hoy. - Hello.
你好  你刚刚说了你好
Hello. You just said hello.
我当然要说"你好"
Of course I said "hello",
没想到你先说了"喂喂"
I was surprised that you said "ahoy-hoy",
我以为是我先说"喂喂"
I thought I was going to say "ahoy-hoy" first,
然后你再说"喂喂"  所以我才说你好
and then you said "ahoy-hoy". That's why I said hello.
-你好  -先生  你得
- Hello. - Ah! Sir, you have to...
算了  我还是拿走它吧
It doesn't matter. I'm going to take these away.
不  等等  我才刚找到窍门
No, wait, I was just getting the hang of it.
事实上  我有办法可以改良这个设计
In fact, I think I can improve on the design.
真心不觉得你能  先生
I very much doubt it, sir,
爱迪生改良了电话设计
你连基本的电话问候语都掌握不了
you cannot even grasp the official telephone greeting.
人们在电话里都说你好
Imagine a world
这样的世界真可笑
where people say into the telephone, "hello."
再见
Goodbye.
他引领了在电话里说你好的潮流
你好  你好  我这出了点问题
Hello. Hello, I think I have a problem.
另一位维多利亚时代发明是摄影
Another Victorian invention was photography.
说"茄子"  我经常这样做
Say, "cheese", I always do.
你  别再浪费时间画画了
You! Kiss goodbye to time-consuming painting,
因为现在是照片时代
because photography is here.
照片时代
-什么  -没听错  你想知道的一切
- What? - Yes, and we've got everything you need to know
照片记事月刊
都在我们全新的照片记事月刊上
in our new Photographic Monthly Chronicle.
你们好  我是Henry Fox Talbot
Hello, I'm Henry Fox Talbot,
维多利亚时代最杰出的摄影创始者之一
one of the great Victorian pioneers of photography.
凭借偶精湛滴摄影技巧
And, with my handy tips,
你就可以拥有像这样的照片
you'll be able to take photographs like this.
以及这样的  甚至是这样的
And this. And even this.
只需要曝光几分钟
With exposure times of several minutes,